Okay,
we're now the text says
uh we should go to the bottom there.
Yeah, deep top line going there.
I don't know. I'm learning. Can I
remember me too but you used to.
Uh if you can
die
with the five powers
then definitely you won't go to any bad
place. You see?
And in this book um
it's long.
Uh
it's very long and that's why it took so
far.
How many years? 13 years.
And um
he will say something like if you can
die with the five powers then you're
going to go to a good place.
And then he's
the book is too long so he doesn't tell
you the five powers.
And that's why we have the ALL database,
Asian Legacy Library. We are fortunate
tonight to have the director, John Brady
is here. And can you please stand up?
Yeah.
And
they have input and by the way Kelsang
helped a lot with starting uh the ALL
many years ago. He helped us start it.
And they have input
total I think it's uh
if I'm not mistaken including the doctor
R
is about 6 million pages or 12?
I don't
over 6 million pages finished and
they're free online. The and then we
have to preserve the pages and then we
have to type them in. We have to input
them.
When you input them, you can search
Uh so, we have a database
of about 15,000 books finished.
And it took 35 years of hard work.
And John's been helping all of this
time. And um
so, when I when the author
says something like five powers, you
should die with the five powers,
and then he doesn't tell you the five
powers,
uh I go to the database and I
take it out of the database. And we have
a incredible search program, very, very
powerful search program.
And uh I can find it there. I'll show it
to you maybe.
Uh
here.
I think it will show on my screen, Tim.
Am I right?
Yeah? You can see?
No.
Forget it. Okay.
Uh
anyway, I'll show it to you sometime. I
can search uh
many I can search 3 million pages in
less than half a second.
And then I can cut out the five powers
and give them to you.
And that's because of John Brady's work
for 35 years. So, let's give him
He's
Prater.
Fundraising Prater.
He'd go around the world like a ghost
looking for donation for ALR. You
understand what I say?
So, give him a donation if you can,
okay? While you're here. While he's
here.
It doesn't have to be a million dollars.
I mean
the gold clubs are are doing $5 a month
or something and
and they reached a million and a half
dollars, so
uh
give him something, okay?
And he's still he's 10% finished.
He has to work for another 350 years.
Okay? So
we should give him, you know, a little
bit of tea money.
Okay? All right. Okay.
Don't laugh there, couple of something
there.
Uh so the first of the five powers is
called the
Say again?
The first of the five powers is called
Oh, somebody give a donation?
Are we splitting, John?
No, okay.
Okay, okay.
Uh
Don't laugh there, couple of something
there.
Uh the first of the five powers is
called the white seed.
The power of the white seed. So you guys
know seven.
Uh bija in Sanskrit and it's a
white seed. And I took notes here, you
can read the notes.
It means uh
take care of things before you die.
Okay? And get things ready. My parents
were
they both got cancer. Both of my parents
got cancer.
And
uh
my dad
was a big big man. Almost as big as
Igor.
And
uh strong.
he got cancer and then he died
slowly and he said, "I'm going to I'm
not going to die. I'm going to fight
this thing."
And uh
then he died.
it took 2 years to figure out his
his finances. It took 2 years
to find out where is all the money and
in the end it was zero.
Completely zero. It was funny.
Uh but it was a lot of trouble for for
the family. You know, he did not prepare
to die. And then my mom
uh
I'll never forget it. She had four sons.
And she brought us into her bedroom. And
she said, "I want to show you
something."
And she unbuttoned her shirt
like this, you know. And she said,
"Touch.
Here there's a bump.
Touch it, you know. You guys can touch
it." And we're so shy to see my mother's
chest, you know. We're like, "Why are
you showing me, Mom?"
She said, "This going to kill me.
Now, I'm going to die.
And uh I want you guys to know. I want
you to understand. This is a cancer and
uh I have to die.
So, let's get ready." She's like, "Let's
get ready." And we're like, "What do we
do, Mom?" And she's like, "Okay, you're
going to take care of this and you're
going to take care of this and we'll
give money to the church and we'll give
money to the poor people."
And she planned everything very nicely.
And then she died.
And uh it was such a difference between
the two
father and the mother, you know. And
in in our Buddhist tradition, we really
encourage you to get ready.
And uh don't think, "Oh, I'm I'm not
71.
I'm 30. I'm 40."
Hey, we don't know who's going to go
first.
You know, we don't know. Nobody knows.
You know, some people got run over on
the way home from Lam Rim.
They got hit by a car.
And they they they don't come to the
second day.
You know, it happens. So, get ready. Get
everything ready. And you feel so happy.
I can tell you. I I I do it. I live this
way.
Everything's ready, you know. Grandpa
die, everything's ready.
And uh it's very relaxing, okay? And
it's kind of fun.
You know, you say, "Hey, you're going to
get this stuff and you're going to
this much money coming to you.
You get this blue car.
You know, and then make every plan make
it clear, okay?
And that's a long run practice, okay?
Don't don't
make your family suffer or your husband
or your wife.
Get everything ready, you know, be
ready.
And do it happy. Don't don't be like,
"Oh, I'm going to die. Oh, no."
"I'm going to die. Yeah. And you can
have my car.
And you can have the bank account and
even Rob, you can have my computer,
okay?"
Oh, guess not. You're not going to take
it with you.
Who gets your backpack? Uh, shut up.
Okay.
Uh
I don't I didn't decide yet. Okay.
Okay, number two, combito. Say combito.
Yeah, and it means uh the
power of good habit, okay? Habit.
And it
Here it means uh
get ready to die in the right frame of
mind, okay? You practice sometimes. My
teacher asked me every night when I go
to bed, I do my coffee meditation.
And then he said, "Do a little bit of
death meditation. If I die tonight,
uh I hope I can go someplace to help
people. I hope I can do something that
will help people. I hope I can help all
beings
uh as I die." And and get ready that
way, okay? That's called
uh
habit, comb.
That's the past tense of comb, okay?
Comb means get get used to it.
Get comfortable with dying, okay? And
don't don't avoid it and don't be
scared, okay? Take care of it. If you
take care of it, you don't have to be
scared.
If you don't take care of it, you have
to be scared.
Okay?
So, take care of it first
and then don't die.
Okay? Then you're ready to die when it
comes time to die.
And I I again it's very
comfortable. It's not depressing.
What's depressing is to try to pretend
that you're not going to die.
That's depressing.
Uh but if you if you say to yourself,
"Okay,
you know, it's flesh and blood. It has
to die."
You know, get used to it and and be
ready. Get ready. Take care of
everything.
I have everything ready. Everything's
ready. All the money, everything.
The things.
It's all taken care of, you know. I do I
work on it every week.
And I take care of things, you know,
when I die. Get ready.
And then uh if you don't die, okay.
It's everything's ready.
If you're going to go to Kyoto,
you're really stupid if you don't pack
uh 2 days before.
You know,
it's very
uh
I don't know.
You feel very crazy if you have to pack
the same day.
You know, you feel stressed out, right?
You have to pack the same day.
So, pack a suitcase for dying.
And do it while you're young.
And just get it ready, you know? And
then you don't have to think about it.
And then you're ready to die. And
and it's a good habit to talk to your
family. It's a good My mom
she loved us a lot,
but she wasn't afraid to talk about it,
you know? She said, "Look,
everybody's going to die.
I'm getting ready."
And we we felt comfortable with her.
We felt, "Okay, Mom."
You know, and we loved her more than
anything in the world.
But we're like, "Okay, Mom." You know,
she said, "Let's get ready." "Okay,
Mom."
And uh we should be like that, okay? All
of us should be like that.
Okay, number three, Pembado. Uh
That's a prayer uh after the Bardo.
Wherever I go,
I hope I don't forget Bodhicitta, okay?
It's Pemba means to
project something into the future, okay?
And you can project this wish,
you know, I hope
after I finish the Bardo,
I hope I can remember my motivation that
I want to help other people. I mean,
I don't
I cannot keep the car.
I cannot keep the clothes. I cannot keep
the
the skin. I cannot keep.
But at least my motivation, I hope I can
keep. Okay, okay. I hope I don't forget
it, okay?
So, make this prayer. That's called
Pembado.
Projection uh into the future.
Okay, you guys know Penjikile.
Projecting karma. You okay? Okay.
Number four, Numbersengim Bado. We have
this
This is the name of one of the four
powers,
and it means the power of destruction.
And uh
in the four powers of confession,
it means to to
When you do your confession,
you feel strong uh regret, and you
decide not to do it again.
And that destroys the karma, okay? So,
Numbersengim Bado
It means to destroy,
and it means to rip something out from
the
Like if you're pulling weeds or
something, rip them out.
It's also an old word for raping
somebody.
Okay, so it means like very violent
uh ripping up. Number sin jumble top.
And it means
uh
do a good confession as you die. Okay,
and it's very very famous
that when you die, as you die,
if before you die,
if you can confess your bad deeds,
you know, I think all of us have a few
bad deeds that we hide
and we don't want to tell anybody.
And it's good before you die,
it's good if you can tell somebody
uh your worst bad deeds, your secret bad
deeds, you know, it's good to tell
somebody.
Uh it's very very powerful to tell
somebody. So, it's it's very important
uh before you die to to tell somebody.
And my dad, when he got a cancer,
I went to stay with him.
There was nothing to do.
It's too late, you know, he's dying
slowly every day.
I watched football with him many hours
cuz he he can't do anything else. And
he's just in a chair and he's And I make
orange juice for him.
He can't eat anything. He's just dying
in a chair and I
I thought uh he has a lot Here's
something you should remember.
If someone you love is dying,
then help them to do a confession. Okay,
help them to do a confession.
And uh
I know he killed many people.
He was in the military uh during World
War II.
And I know he killed many people in the
military and um
So, I and he doesn't like to talk about
it. Never. He never talk about it.
And uh I thought
uh
it's better if he tell me
before he dies. It's better if he tells
somebody
what he did, you know. So, we are
watching football.
As he can't do anything else.
And I'm making orange juice for him, you
know.
And I'm like, "Dad, can you tell me a
little bit about the war?" I said,
"Would you kill again? Would you do it
again?"
You know, I tricked him, actually. I
said,
"If if you in the same situation again,
would you kill people again?"
And he said, "No. I I would never do
that." Then, that's pure confession.
Then, he destroyed that karma. Mostly,
he destroyed the sin. When you say,
"I will never do it again." That's
number sin generator. That's power of
destruction.
And I was so happy. I was like,
you know, now he can die clean, okay?
So, it's Try to even you have to trick
them.
People they don't want to talk about
things or be honest about uh
your own
Be be ready to tell somebody your worst
things.
And you can get rid of those things
before you die, okay? So,
if you're dying, who cares what you did?
They're going to
Let me tell you something. They're going
to forget later, anyway.
So, tell them. Tell people Don't be shy.
You're dying.
So, what Who cares? They won't even
remember your name later.
So,
tell your worst things
and clean clean your heart. And then you
can die happily, and you can die clean.
And it's very, very, very important,
okay? If you get hit by a car
and you're bleeding to death and then
somebody says, "Are you okay?" You say,
"No, I'm dying. By the way, I did this
terrible thing."
Just tell them, okay?
Tell somebody, okay? It doesn't matter.
It doesn't have to be a
a monk or a priest or a teacher. Tell
anybody.
You know, I I heard one guy told his
dog.
He was dying. He told the dog,
"I killed somebody." I can't r-
And he got it off, okay? Clean your
heart.
And then you can die happy, okay? All
right. Number five, Manom Kito.
Uh
And I made a note for you here. It says
Dukshing means uh Buddha paradise.
Pure pure field, Dukshing.
And then they say uh
in the Lam Rim
when you're dying
you don't say, "Oh, I hope I can go to
Amitabha's paradise. I hope I do give me
I can go there. I hope she has room."
You know,
don't talk like that, okay?
Uh
the big motivation is, "I hope
I can take all the bad seeds of
everybody else and die."
You know, then just I will I will carry
those bad seeds out of this world.
And those people don't have them. Is it
possible?
Not really. You can't do it, okay?
Buddha cannot take one seed from you.
So, why you do this stupid prayer, you
know? I hope I can take everyone's bad
seeds.
When I die, I will be like uh There was
an old Christian custom, a Jewish custom
called uh Lamb of God.
And uh they will once a year
in Jerusalem they will make prayer.
Put all the bad karma into one small
baby
goat
and go kill it in the desert.
And that's where the expression lamb of
God came from for Jesus.
So the idea was everyone can put their
bad karma in a
animal and then they kill the animal. Of
course that's a terrible
mistake.
But the idea is good. The idea is pretty
good, okay. I can be the lamb. You give
me all your bad seeds and I will die
with it. I pray I could do it.
You cannot do it, but if you pray
it will clean your seeds, okay? Good way
to die.
Good way to die is to wish you could
take everyone's bad karma with you.
Give me your bad karma, I'm dying.
And give it to me, I'll take care of it.
I you know
Okay, it's a nice motivation.
Sometimes you can do that.
Okay, dun sang ngapa. Ngapa dun sang
ngapa means uh
of the seven point
lojong, seven point bodhisattva
practice.
We're on number five. We reached number
five. Ngapa means fifth, okay.
Lojong bet se means uh
Se means Some of you guys know the word
sema
or pramana
which means the measurement, okay?
And in this context se means
what's the point at which you have
developed
lojong.
Okay?
I Do you have lojong?
I studied it with Geshe La, but do you
have it?
I don't know. How do you know?
Oh, there's a se. There's a
There's a definition of when you have
lojong, okay? When you got it, here's
When you got this, you got it. When you
don't got this, you don't got it.
Okay. That's called sin. Okay.
Uh
Yeah, and then
uh
I cut it out of the of the ACI course
course 14. It's there. Okay. If you're
interested, it's there.
And the
the point at which you have the
the point at which you can say you have
the good heart is in course 14. Okay.
ACI course 14.
And these are some comments
about how do you know when you have
lojong. How do you know when you got it?
And here's By the way, if you heard it
in New York in 19
or something,
it doesn't hurt to hear it again.
Okay. We forgot anything? Okay, so here
we go.
Uh
I'm going to go through these uh it's
four mainly four points. Okay. But we'll
go through them. Okay.
And there's a dividing line
picture.
Next picture. Yeah. It just means uh
what's the
ultimate dividing line? Something's
Dharma or it's not Dharma. Okay.
Uh and I put a bold for the root text.
This is the root text of Geshe Chekhawa.
Okay. Or Lord Atisha.
Uh Chekung Gonpa Chikyudu. All Dharma
comes down to a single point. Okay. All
Dharma comes down to one idea. All
Dharma comes down to one idea. What's
that?
Chomden Dekyi Chiphung Gyene Chig Suma.
Chiphung is a idea. It's uh
one pile of Dharma teachings. okay? One
mountain
of Dharma teachings. And there's a
measure
uh
of
how many pages of Dharma teachings,
okay? And it's 84,000
mountains of Dharma teaching. Buddha
taught 84,000 mountains
of Dharma teaching, okay?
Uh some that they could ship on genetic.
No matter how many mountains of Dharma
teaching he taught,
uh some that function taking number
show. Show is an old verb
that means all the rivers reach to the
same ocean, okay? It means that show
means all the rivers go to the same
ocean.
Uh
all the
Buddhist teachings that Lord Buddha ever
gave,
they go to one ocean. And that ocean is
can you stop your habit of taking care
of yourself first?
Okay, all all Dharma teachings, all all
books, all scriptures, all translations,
all all everything
comes down to one question.
Can can you stop
your habit of taking care of yourself
first? Can you stop it? Okay.
He says she do show, okay?
Bob latch. Bob Bob means the river falls
to the ocean.
Okay, children should remember Nam take.
Take is a nice word. Um we do a lot of
takes
when we draw mandalas.
And uh
when you when you make a mandala, it's
very complex and it's very precise, and
you have to use uh geometry.
And that's sometimes called tick. You
you draw
we call snap a line in uh in
construction.
You hold the two ends of the string, and
you have colored powder on the string,
and you
you snap it, and that's called a tick.
It's a line, okay? okay? Num tick means
what's the dividing line
between cha and chamin. What's the
What's the dividing line between Dharma
and not Dharma, okay? What's the
dividing line? Gyang
nyom ngag nyam pa so ma song.
If something helps you stop your bad
thoughts, it's Dharma.
If it doesn't, it's not.
That's the definition of Dharma. That's
the tick. That's the dividing line for
Dharma, okay? Oh, I went to a Dharma
class. Yeah? Was it Dharma?
I don't know. Was it Dharma? I
Did it help you become a better person?
Yes. Okay, it was Dharma.
It was Dharma, okay? Doesn't matter
where it was.
You can go any If someone
helps you to be a better person, if
someone helps you remove your negative
emotions, it's Dharma. That's a very
interesting.
If someone teaches you a bunch of
Tibetan sentences and it doesn't help
you remove your negative emotions, it's
not a Dharma teaching.
I don't know. If you go to a
psychologist and they teach you
something nice
and it helps you mentally, then that's
Dharma.
That's very beautiful, right? Hey, I
went to the Buddhist teaching. I didn't
hear any Dharma.
And then I came home and listened to my
kids and they were talking Dharma.
You know, it's like that. Okay, who
teaches you to be a better person?
They are teaching you Dharma.
And I don't know, there's a lot of
teachings in the monastery Geshe course
where people just get more and more
proud and more and more competitive
and then that's not Dharma, okay? They
spent 25 years
but they didn't study Dharma.
Got it? Okay. Those
When you go somewhere and someone tells
you something that makes you a better
person, that's Dharma.
And if you go somewhere and they talk
about Buddhism for 5 hours and then it
doesn't make you a better person, it's
not Dharma. Got it?
That's Dharma.
Okay.
All right.
Next picture.
Uh
Ultimate sign of success, okay.
And that's called Drup Tak. Say Drup
Tak.
Drup means uh Siddha.
Right? Drup means to spiritual go go or
spiritual achievements, okay? Tak means
in this case uh sign. Sign of
achievement, you know? Am I successful
in my Dharma practice or not? There's a
Drup Tak.
What's a Drup Tak? Drup Tak a Chok. Chok
means supreme. Like Konchok means uh
three jewels, okay?
What's the highest sign of all that you
are succeeding in your Buddhist
practice?
To Nyomong Je Chung La Song.
If your negativities get less and less
every day,
you are a successful Buddhist, okay? If
your negative
thoughts, negative emotions, negative
behavior,
if it gets less and less every day,
then then the Dharma's having effect on
you, okay? That is Dharma and you are
practicing Dharma. If you become a
better person
every day,
it's Dharma and Drup Tak Drup Tak means
you're you're a successful Dharma
practitioner. If you get a little bit
better every day. By the way,
it's not a lot better every day. That
doesn't happen.
Okay? And I'm just being honest, okay?
Little little progress every day, that's
fine.
It's just like when you're trying to
learn a language or
or you're trying to learn some business
skill or something. If you get a little
bit better every day,
it's success, okay? Don't expect
this, you know, don't expect all your
jealousies going to go away in 20 years.
It doesn't work.
Okay? It takes longer than that, okay?
But keep keep a little bit get a little
bit better every day, and then you're
you're practicing Dharma, okay? And your
your bad habits are not going to go away
in one day or one year.
It doesn't happen like that. I can tell
you grandpa, that's why I'm a grandpa.
Okay? It doesn't happen like that. Make
little bit of progress every day. Are
you better than last week? Yes. Are you
good? No.
But are you better than last week? Yes,
well that's good.
Then you're good, okay? So just
little bit of improvement every every
year, okay? Every year a little bit
better person, okay? And then that's
success. That's Drukpa. Then you're a
Siddha.
Mahasiddha.
Okay? Drukpa, okay? Sökyong.
Uh they mean by Namgyal Chökyi Gyaltsen
Kunga Sangye Chökyi Gyaltsen
Chökyi Nyima Gyaltsen
Chökyi Nyima Drukpa Shenpen
Tingzin Zangpo
Then he said a cute thing. Um
he said sign of progress
is that you're a little bit better
person every year.
Okay? Then you're then you're making
progress, okay? Then he says, "Look,
uh Jamyang Khyentse Namkha Gyaltsen
it's not flying in the sky, okay? Oh, he
fly in the sky, he's success in his
Dharma.
Yeah, but he fly in the sky and he's
pissed off at people all the time.
He
He's a failure, Dharma failure, you see?
So he's he says here he said something
cute. He says, "Look, birds also fly in
the sky.
You know, what's the big deal?
You know, just cuz you can fly in the
sky doesn't mean you're
Dharma success. It's are you less
jealous
each year? Are you are you less
irritable each year? Small progress.
Okay? Not fly in the sky, okay?
Some really stupid person
uh
There was a discussion whether Geshe
Michael's an Arhat and some really
stupid person said, "He's not." And they
said, "Why?" And they said, "He can't
fly in the sky."
And I went,
"Okay. So, here here it is, okay?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Anyway,
uh Salong Drolchok means, "Look,
there's
there's a city where you can fly in the
sky.
And there's a city where you can burrow
underground. You can walk It's called
underground. So,
and you can uh like you can go back to
the Western Hotel underground
without having to walk across the
crosswalk, okay? It And you walk through
the solid earth
underground, okay? He says, "Ah,
mice do the same thing.
Okay? That doesn't mean you're a siddha
a siddha,
okay? Just cuz you can walk through
solid rock,
it doesn't make That's not the real
siddha. The real siddha is
are you less jealous than last year?
Or are you are you less desire than last
year? Then then that's progress.
But just walking through a wall,
you know, even mice do that.
Okay?
Then he says,
uh there's another siddha where you can
uh
walk through water.
Like you can walk under a river and, you
know, through the river.
Under the river and and go to the other
side, like grandma walk or something.
And uh
He says, "Ah,
fish do that.
You know, even fish can do that. Chill
chill
chill uh
chill that me young chill chill chill
fish also
can walk through the water. It's not a
big deal, okay? If you can control your
competitiveness
in the business, you made progress.
You you made real progress. You're
saint. You then you're a saint.
Okay? But just cuz you can fly in the
sky or walk through walls and that's not
the sign of a saint, okay?
Mice do that. Fish do that.
No big deal, okay? Got it?
Okay.
Uh
What's the timing, uh Jim?
Until Q&A.
15. 8:45 I start Q&A. 6:45. Okay, good.
Okay.
Uh Lojong dilo che don che men da pe
sang du sum pe
Uh sang s r a n g means uh a scale. You
know, like the old scale that you weigh
vegetables on or something. That's
called a sang.
And uh he said
the practice of Lojong is the scale.
You know, whether
you can use your Lojong practice to
decide to measure your success. Lojong
is the scale where you can measure your
Dharma success.
Uh sang du sum pe
che je be long je la don chen ze chu mo
so wa
du na jong bo
Uh long je means
uh
fingerprint or handprint. Uh
gong je is the what you call footprint.
So, print means uh
in in Dharma teachings, gunjay means uh
sign of success.
Okay, in your practice is called your
footprint
or your hand print. Okay, so the the
hand print
of successful Dharma
is
did your selfishness get less or not?
Did your selfishness get less or not? If
If your selfishness
is getting less every year,
that's a sign of success. Okay, that's a
good sign of success. It's
It's like the fingerprint in the murder
mystery or something.
Oh, someone here
was a good person. How do you know?
They I saw the sign. What's the sign?
They are less selfish than last year.
Okay, less selfish than last year. Sign
of
success. Okay, footprint of success or
hand print of success. Okay.
Okay, next
picture.
That was the
That's supposed to be the justice scale.
All right, next picture.
Mhm.
I planted
all these peach trees in my house and
all of them died.
Then two friends came from Shin Jen
and they came to my cafe and they
planted two trees and they grew like
crazy.
And
I even sold the peaches and I did not
give them any money.
And uh
Anyway, we're standing outside and this
is one of the trees.
Uh
and they they planted it uh at the cafe.
And good job, you guys I don't
I don't know what they put there.
Bambo Niki Tsong is in so the the Lodong
text
the text about
Bodichita attitude
it says
uh
mainly keep the two judges keep the main
one of the two judges Bambo means
witness
or judge okay Bambo it's a little bit
unusual word these words are a thousand
years old.
So it's a little bit difficult it's one
of the seven languages eight languages
okay Bambo Bambo means witness or judge
okay.
Uh he says the main judge keep the main
judge who is it?
Uh did I mix up the two pictures? I
don't know anyway Rang Shing Get Bambo
Niki De.
Rang Nyam Shawa Make Yang Tsug Chig Get
so
if there's two witnesses to your
behavior if there's two witnesses to
your mental state
uh which one is more important?
You or other people?
Who knows your mental state better?
Yeah yeah yeah but we tend to try to
look good to other people.
Like we don't care if we look good to
our self.
Our mind is dirty and we live with it.
It's fine.
But we want to pretend to other people
Geshe La wants to look very holy in the
teaching.
And then he goes home and watch Netflix
all night. Or Korean soap operas.
You know he want to look nice you know.
So
so this ancient Lodong text says
who should you impress?
Who who should you impress? Should you
impress the audience who comes to your
teaching?
Or should you impress yourself in
private? Which is more important?
Yourself. Yeah, you're the one who knows
who you are.
Don't try to pretend to other people.
You We tend to try to look good to other
people. And we don't care how dirty we
look to ourself.
And he said you should switch it, you
know.
So,
there's many many famous teachers who
like didn't take a bath for a week.
Just so other people don't judge them
wrong.
But inside they're very pure.
To themselves, they're pure. To other
people, they don't look pure. That
They're happy that way. They're They're
like that.
Okay? So, don't try to look good to
others.
Try to look good to yourself in your own
heart.
You know, you should be able to look at
your own heart and say, "That's a
beautiful thing." That's really
beautiful, you know, instead of
how much makeup, you know, we call
Sephora, right? Expensive also.
You guys don't go to Sephora in Kyoto.
You can't get eager. You can't get out
of there unless they're $100.
Impossible. Okay, I don't care what
others say.
Uh
you know, it's expensive, okay? So, it's
much cheaper to put makeup on the
inside, okay? Like it's much
You should be beautiful on the inside.
And don't worry, you know, the outside
maybe we're beautiful, maybe we're not.
Uh but be beautiful on the inside. You
You're the judge. You're the ultimate
judge of your beauty, not somebody else.
Okay? You decide whether you're
beautiful or not, not other people.
Okay? Got it? Cool.
By the way, if you if you look inside
and you're beautiful, you are really
beautiful and you feel beautiful, okay?
Uh the outside beauty is very
difficult to keep it. It lasts for a few
years and
then you got to use more and more
makeup.
Then it's like ridiculous. It's like a
whole bottle of makeup just to get out
in the morning.
And okay, so take care of the inside. Be
sexy on the inside.
And that's really sexy. And then outside
uh
you know, it's going to fall apart.
Okay. All right. Uh Bob Menendez
Shangyit said that Zinkyong other people
tend to judge us.
Suchin Sangdokha Sang
Suchin Sangdokha Sangba Tsiwa
Sangchunyong
You and me, we tend to kind of
put on a false appearance to other
people, like we're better people than we
really are. Okay.
Sometimes I like to just mess up in
front of other people and then the
pressure's off, you know. Geshe Losang
idiot, yeah.
Uh then it's so relaxing. I don't have
to try to look smart, you know.
Okay. Uh Chungyong
Daytsamni Amideva Chinang Memami Nerik
Shisumba
Uh Nagarjuna's letter to the king, one
of Udai Bhadra, one of his two letters
to the king.
Uh he goes off on mango fruits, okay?
And uh it's a big subject in India cuz
once a year the mangoes come out.
I was there in mango season. The first
the first week that the mangoes are
ripe,
they're like $10 a bag.
Second week, they're $8 a bag. Third
week, they're $4 a bag.
You know, sixth week, everyone's trying
to give away mangoes.
And uh
and they're high. They grow very high
and then they're hard to judge the from
the color.
It's hard to judge whether it's ripe or
not. And you know, the kid, you pay a
kid to climb up the tree and squeeze it
for you.
And they're very famous
example for what?
Is a person really a good person? We
don't know.
They're people are like mangoes.
Some people look really nice on the
outside and they're really lousy on the
inside. Some people look really lousy on
the outside and they're really pure on
the inside.
You know, people There's so many
gardeners I used to say, "Ah, people are
mangoes.
You know, I'm so tired of trying to
judge the mangoes."
Who knows, you know? Some people look
sweet on the outside and they're really
bad on the inside. We don't know, okay?
So, he says,
uh
dead double
Okay, chill out Jabba you teaching.
What is that Kel Sang? Sheila Jabba.
Jabba means hiding?
Sheila's in a in a mouth?
All right.
Sheila Sheila
Oh, Sheila is a rat, I think.
Okay, he agree.
Uh
Yeah, he said
um
rats tend to hide in a hole, okay?
Meaning you can't judge a person from
the outside.
Uh
dead double la che che mi she pe ta ki
sa me cha di zim ma Sometimes we There's
a person who's really mean on the
inside, but we think they look really
nice on the outside.
Uh den da wa da mi cha shi. Don't be the
kind of person who pretends to be a holy
person on the outside and is rotten on
the inside or cruel on the inside, okay?
All right. Shen Yang
nang mi la chi He's giving the possible
What do you call it? Permutations.
Mango looks good on the outside and
lousy on the inside. Mango looks
good on the inside, looks lousy on the
outside. Mango is lousy and looks lousy
and mango looks good and he's good. Four
It's the four famous mangoes. Okay.
Shkenya nang men la chi me men means uh
the sometimes the mango is ripe on the
inside but it looks on the outside and
looks like it's not. So, sometimes the
person on the outside looks kind of mean
but they have a big heart
on the inside. Okay? Like a
outside looks like a bad mango but
inside is a good mango. Okay?
Memba uh me memba memba
uh chi du e shingye che ma gopa
uh
shingye che
ma gopa dong che che ya what's that?
che ya
uh lots che ya but che ya the same lots
uh
che ya
lots uh
same lots uh
I don't really care what you say. I'm
trying to keep you awake. lots uh
che ya
Okay. Uh these are in the Abhidharma
Kosha and there's uh
all virtuous states of mind are
accompanied by two
two states of mind in the Abhidharma
standing. What are they?
Yeah, we can say shame and
consideration. Okay? In the Abhidharma
Kosha system
uh all good
every time you do a good deed
there's two mental states going on. One
is
you do care what other people think of
you.
Okay? So, I don't know. A lot of times
Geshe la will not play Netflix in front
of the audience.
But when he goes home, he will play
Netflix.
So, in the public, he doesn't play
Netflix, but when he gets home, he plays
Netflix, okay?
That's called
chö
chö yo.
I care about what other people think. I
do care.
I always try to get home before I watch
Korean soap opera.
Okay? Then ngönsa means
uh you have a chance to watch Netflix in
your own
hotel room. There's nobody there.
And nobody will know
if you watch it. But you you say to
yourself,
"This is not who I want to be.
This is not who I want to be." So,
according to Abhidharma,
there's two kinds of virtuous
states of mind.
One is
"This is not who I want people to see me
as." And that's okay. That's healthy,
you know? That's healthy. I don't want
to look like a bad person.
And then ngönsa, you're it's even more
powerful. And that means in the privacy
of my own home,
when nobody can see me, I still want to
be good to myself cuz I care. I care how
my self-esteem.
I don't want to be a bad person even in
in my own room
when nobody else can see me.
Okay? So, here he's talking about
uh nang tül-gyi rang-gyü nyönam gyi
chöpa, chitsang,
ngönsang. We want to be pure on the
outside and pure on the inside.
Good mangoes.
Good peaches.
Peaches are pretty easy, I think, cuz
they
the outside is pretty honest, okay?
All right.
Uh Chandra Sambhava
ni chapa nyempa po me che che pa tar
chi kun je kyan chapa nyempa shi nam
pang de sab de tso rang kyi rang na
ni tewa shi kyol che so
Bodhisattvas
chapa nyempa po me che means
if they get some kind of bad reputation
in the world, that's not their main or
they don't think about it mainly, okay?
That's not what they're mainly worried
about, okay? If somebody's What do you
call that on the internet? Trolling them
on the internet.
They don't waste their time to to defend
themselves, okay? They're like
okay, chapa nyempa po me che means
I don't care what people say about me.
In a good way, you know, it's like,
okay, people say I'm a bad person, I'm
not.
Okay, chapa nyempa po me che. They don't
waste their time trying to prove to
everybody on the internet that they're a
good person, okay?
They just be a good person, okay?
Chi chi kun je kyan chapa nyempa shi nam
pang ni sab de
Their their main
interest is not trying to look like a
good person, it's to be a good person.
Their main effort is to be
inside a good person and if their main
effort is not to look like a good
person. Although they care about it,
they they I mean we should care, right?
We shouldn't
uh
we don't want people to think we're a
bad person and it's important for a good
person to think about that.
But the most important thing is to be
good on the inside, no matter what
people think about you on the outside,
okay?
And if you're going to spend time
either to fight the trolls in the world
or to fight your own mental afflictions,
probably you should work on the
afflictions and the trolls will take
care of themselves.
Okay? And I that's my philosophy. I I I
I don't want to waste time trying to
prove I'm a nice person. I think I'll
just focus on being a nice person.
Sooner or later the internet will catch
up.
I mean,
that's my philosophy. Okay. Shamatha
shikan chos sam, very important. Okay.
Uh
Okay, next one, smiling guy. Yende
bashik yende ten. Be joy alone in an
unbroken stream. Okay. Tim, what time
I'm supposed to
Q&A? Now?
Whenever I like. Uh tomorrow?
Uh
I think it's now, right?
Okay, that's a good place to pause.
It is a good place. It's a good place to
stop. Okay.
Uh
And the next one, uh the next advice
uh is about uh
focusing on having fun.
Okay. And I I don't know. A lot of
Dharma people are too serious for me.
You know, they're all like, "Om mani
padme
Om mani padme
And you know, you If you're having
If you know what's going to happen after
you die, if you know where you're going,
uh
then okay, relax, have fun. Go out We we
went out last night, right?
We had a good time.
Somebody said, "Geshe la, you should go
to the hotel from the airport."
Maybe somebody's waiting for the flowers
or something. I said, "No way. I'm going
to go out and have a really good
dinner."
So, I kidnapped everybody.
And we went out We we did in Rimrock.
There's no restaurants there.
You know, if you get to go to Kyoto or
go to go to I mean, I'm going to go to
the restaurant, you know. So, have fun.
You know, life is short.
And I I think if you really practice
good Lamrim,
uh you should have fun. I don't mean fun
like you go gambling or
or alcohol or I I don't mean like that.
I mean,
you know, relax and have some fun, you
know.
Life is so short.
And I if you're too serious, I think
your your Buddhism is weird.
Okay? All right?
Okay? Have some fun. If you're really
doing good Buddhism,
you should be in a good mood, right? I
think so. And then have some fun, you
know. It's okay. Good fun, clean fun.
Okay.
All right, Timothy. Uh questions.
Uh my question is how to correctly
understand the famous verse from
Nagarjuna, which is no starting, no
stopping, and no staying. We slightly
touched this by DCI level 12 like 210,
which is saying that it's not a seed
cause the result. In fact, the seed and
the result are existing at the same
time. So, that means right now me and
the the whatever the dream me is already
existing at the same time. Also, we from
level 11 we learned that the time
doesn't exist really. So, that means
everything existing at the same time
now. So, me and the perfect me or the
dream me existing now at the same time.
Then, why all these? Or what is the
direct fast to track for that perfect
me?
And also, we learned in
uh DCI level seven everything's coming
from the seeds. Everything have
emptiness. So, that means emptiness also
have emptiness. And the seeds principle
also have emptiness. But, in level two,
we learn that the seeds principle is
just like the gravity. It's applied to
everyone. So, in this way, how to really
understand the seeds principle also have
emptiness.
So, that's basically my question. So,
thank you very very much.
Wow, that's kind of
I think three translators just had a
hard time.
Uh
No, that's a good question. And I just
finished the book. I was working on a
book.
Uh
I work on books all year. Uh and I was
working on Nick Lashaw's book. Nick's
coming, which is exciting to me.
And he he translated Nagarjuna's
60 verses
uh
on proving Nyaya, on proving emptiness.
So, he he he translated that book.
And uh
in that book
Nagarjuna has a very very big
emphasis
that
uh he he's kind of saying
if you really understand cause and
effect in goal, if you really understand
it
then that's emptiness, you know. And
technically, that's not correct.
Okay. So, there's a big big argument.
I'll say it again.
Nagarjuna in the 60 verses says that
in goal that the fact that cause is
cause
results
is dependent origination. It is
emptiness.
That itself is emptiness. And that's not
true.
It's it's not true. Emptiness cannot
change, for example.
But, a cause has to change to produce a
result, okay? So, it's it seems like
he's
saying something contradictory.
Uh and then some Kapa
about
100 1,200 years later, he says the same
thing.
Oh, the greatest thing Buddha ever
taught was what?
Dependent origination because it is
emptiness.
You know, so that's confusing. I'll say
it again.
Mental states create your world.
And that's changing, okay? Every time a
seed opens,
it's destroyed. When the seed turns into
a tree, the seed dies. Has to,
okay? The seed dies
by giving a tree, right?
So, seeds and results have to change.
Seeds have to change to produce a
result. Otherwise, there won't be a
result. The seed has to disappear.
If the seed is still there, the tree
cannot be there.
Once the tree is there, the seed has to
be gone.
Uh the seed has to be destroyed to make
the tree. It has to be. It's always like
that. Then,
emptiness shouldn't change ever.
Emptiness should always be the same,
okay?
Uh and I'll give you an example, you
ready?
Um
Do you have mouse in your kitchen?
Mouse mice.
I I don't. I mean, sometimes I do, but
not right now.
Okay. Do you have mouse in your kitchen?
I said, "No."
Uh
did you ever catch a mouse in your
kitchen? I have a
Mongolian mouse trap. It's very cool.
No springs, no nothing. It's three one
stick.
Two sticks, three sticks, three sticks.
You can catch any mouse. I don't care
how smart they are, okay? And it's very
cool. The Mongolian guy taught me, okay?
So, if a mouse is in your kitchen, but
you take the mouse out of the kitchen,
then is there a mouse in your kitchen,
yes or no?
Is there emptiness of mouse in your
kitchen?
Is there absence of mouse in your
Yeah, there is. Okay, I'll say it again.
When the mouse is running around pooping
on everything,
uh you have a mouse in your kitchen.
Then when you catch the mouse and you
take them out,
then you create Did you create? Then you
have a thing in your kitchen called no
mouse in the kitchen, okay? Absence of
mouse in the kitchen, okay?
Does the absence of the mouse in the
kitchen ever change?
It cannot change, okay? Why? You can't
have half half a mouse in the kitchen or
something like that. Either mouse is in
the kitchen or a mouse is not in the
kitchen.
There's no other choice, okay?
Uh so,
when the mouse comes back in the
kitchen,
where does the absence of the mouse go?
It just disappears, okay? It doesn't get
smaller smaller smaller smaller smaller.
When the mouse's nose comes into the
door,
then there's less mouse, there's less no
mouse. It doesn't work like that, right?
When the whole mouse is in, then no
mouse went away.
But when the mouse's nose is in,
I don't know. Is there mouse in the
kitchen? Not really.
Okay, so either mouse is there or mouse
isn't there. You can't say half mouse is
not like that, okay? So,
it can go out of existence, but it
cannot change.
Okay, mouse mouse in the kitchen or no
mouse in the kitchen.
No mouse in the kitchen can disappear
when a whole mouse comes in the kitchen,
but it doesn't get bigger or smaller.
Okay, you can't say I have 50% no mouse
in my kitchen.
You can't say that. Either there's a
mouse in your kitchen or there's no
mouse in your kitchen.
So, no mouse cannot change.
You cannot have half mouse.
It's something like that. It doesn't
work like that. I have half mouse not in
my kitchen.
It doesn't work like that. Okay, so
emptiness
cannot change. Absence cannot change.
Okay, it can go away,
but it cannot change. Okay,
got it? So, that's the difference. Seed
seed and result the seed disappear
disappear disappear disappear stop.
Results grow grow grow grow.
Tree grows, but absence
it's either total or it's or it's not
there. Okay, absence has to be total.
Therefore,
absence can change,
but dependent origination. Sorry,
absence cannot change, but dependent
origination can change. So, why
did Nagarjuna say
uh emptiness
emptiness and dependence are the same
thing? Because it's not true. One is
never change, one always change.
Then why did he say something's not
true?
And and I'll tell you, okay? You got to
read Nick's book when it comes out.
And uh it's a very very very sexy book,
okay?
So, in Buddhism
there's two divisions. We call Hinayana
and Mahayana. Lower way, higher way.
Sometimes Hinayana called Theravada,
which means the true way.
If you belong to Hinayana, you call
Hinayana Theravada.
Right? Okay, it's okay.
So, there's a lower way and a higher
way, right? There's two kinds of uh
there's there's two kinds of Buddhism,
right? People say
Lord Buddha
in his first turning of the wheel in his
first
teaching period in this world
he taught Hinayana and that's true. He
taught Hinayana.
And then 700 years later
Nagarjuna came
and he taught Mahayana.
Okay? He changed everything. He said
emptiness is deeper than that
and we all have to try to be
Bodhisattvas. Before that no one talks
about Bodhisattvas. Bodhisattvas
mentioned once in the Abhidharma Kosha.
It's a different thing.
There's no such thing, okay? Everybody
say, "Oh, Nagarjuna is so cool.
He started the Mahayana."
In Nick's book
Nagarjuna says, "I didn't start the
Mahayana. It was always Mahayana."
Okay?
It's so sexy.
You know, he says, "Don't blame me.
I didn't I didn't start this emptiness
thing. Buddha did.
You just didn't understand it. Okay? He
was talking Mahayana all along
and you guys didn't understand it.
Dependence is emptiness."
First teaching of Buddha is dependence.
The first big teaching of Buddha is
dependence.
Then later Nagarjuna start talking about
emptiness and then Nagarjuna said
in the 60 verses, he said to the
Hinayana people, "You guys
don't understand what? Buddha taught
emptiness from the first meaning.
You just didn't understand it. Don't
talk about Hinayana Mahayana. This
ridiculous. He always teach Mahayana.
You're Hinayana.
He's not Hinayana. Got it?
His dependent origination teaching is
god damn emptiness. Don't you
understand?
But he's not saying changing thing is
unchanging. He's not saying that.
He's just saying if you really
understand dependence, it's emptiness.
And and if you think it's different
if you think some guy came along and
started Mahayana later, you're mistaken.
It was emptiness all along.
He just didn't You just didn't
understand him.
And then in the 60 verses
he uses all of their ancient books to
prove
that they are Mahayana and they don't
know it.
Okay.
It's very cool.
Anyway, I I suggest you read next book.
Okay. Then I think your good question.
It's a very beautiful question. It's a
big question.
By the way, we did a cool thing in that
book.
And I have to brag about it cuz Geshe
Michael likes bragging. Um
We went through this the whole book, 60
verses. It took 7 years.
We went through the whole book and we
made a list of the most important ideas.
Okay. Cool. So far cool?
Then
we went to John Brady's database.
And we checked how many of those ideas
survived.
And how many didn't survive.
And it's very interesting. So some of
the greatest ideas
in the Garland did not survive.
Okay. They died.
Uh some someone forgot to teach it in or
and you can prove it with his database.
Statistically, we put percentages on all
the ideas.
That we have got the statistics for all
the great ideas in the Garland.
And it's very interesting. You know, you
can show
statistically
from
1,800 years
that some of the ideas he wanted to
teach
disappeared by bad luck or and it
happens in the monastery, you know, the
teacher gets sick that week
and they don't teach that topic and then
the students, the Geshes don't learn it
and then those Geshes don't teach it to
their Geshe students and the idea
disappears.
And you can statistically show
which ideas
disappeared.
It's very interesting and then uh
it seems like what he wanted to happen
didn't happen.
Cuz he wrote verses that nobody ever
used them after that. Nobody understood
them after that. You can prove
that some of his verses nobody
understood them for 2,000 years cuz they
never used them.
They're missing
from that the data.
They're not in the data. You can prove
it statistically.
Uh
and then I was thinking um
maybe he knew that.
I mean at the end of the whole thing it
took me like a year
to do the statistics and then I'm like
wait a minute, maybe Nagarjuna is
tricking us.
Maybe he wants us to to figure this out.
And he's hoping we'll teach those
those things and wake them back up. You
see what I mean? Like if he's really an
Arya
and maybe he can see
that this idea will have a what do you
call it? A renaissance.
There will be a renaissance of certain
ideas
after John Brady.
Yeah.
You know.
He can.
Yeah.
I I really enjoyed it.
I don't know what you have there.
So, you can read it when it comes out.
I'm sure Rose is going to get it out
quick.
Where is Rose? Okay, are we done?
No, but when
did you want me to be done?
No, I don't want to go too late. I mean,
you should be fresh.
You know, we did a lot today and you've
been very good.
And it's hard to listen to this stuff. I
you don't know how many times I suffered
in the monastery.
You know, the teachers like blah blah
blah.
And I'm like, come on, you're strong.
I always made a promise to myself uh
when I become a geshe and I start
teaching, I'm going to kill the students
in the same way.
Good?